Narrator: Part 2
Interviewer: When was the last time you saw a production of a Shakespeare play yourself?
Diane: I have to confess that I haven’t been to see a Shakespeare play recently, actually.
Well, the most recent one was
– I went to see some students at Central School for Speech and Drama, actually,
so I did go and see Macbeth recently.
So, really, you know, they were really into it and really relishing it…
they did a bit of gender-blind performing, where they had a lot of the women playing male roles;
they actually didn’t have any of the men playing female roles,
which I thought was an interesting choice, that that was weighted in one direction.
Interviewer: What do you think in general about the trend in modern productions
for male roles to be played by women, for example, Glenda Jackson as King Lear?
Diane: I think, you know, theatre needs to be kept alive and fresh,
you need to keep experimenting.
The thing that concerns me is if you’re doing it a) because it’s a gimmick, or b) because it’s kind of trendy.
At the same time, I sympathize with, you know, strong, experienced women actors,
because they don’t have the choice of powerful roles that men do if you’re playing according to gender,
so I think it’s great to give women actors the opportunity to play these hefty roles that Shakespeare
– that are written for male characters in Shakespeare.
Interviewer: What about male actors playing female roles?
Diane: I think it’s all about the actor, isn’t it, and whether the role suits them, so…
You know, there is a slight political agenda there, of,
well, why have men taken even more roles away from women – question mark
– when women are struggling enough?
Interviewer: How would you feel about a male actor playing a female role in one of your plays,
or vice versa?
Diane: I have no problem with men playing women or women playing men in any of my plays.
One of my plays, Poppy and George,
is all about a woman who lives her life as a man because she feels too limited to live her life,
if you like, in women’s clothes in the world in 1919 just after the First World War.
So, in a way it’s a theme of my work that, you know,
the theme of the roles we play in the world, and do they restrict us or do they liberate us?
In terms of, yeah, theatre, I mean, the things that I’ve found difficult
when I’ve seen productions are usually around feeling that an actor isn’t right for the role.
That isn’t about… you know, you can have a person of the gender the character is,
or what the character is, and they – and yet, they’re just not the right person.
So, I think what makes a person be able to bring a role alive fully is about, I suppose,
their empathy, their connection with the character and the themes of the play,
and their skill probably, if we’re talking about professional work.
So, it’s those things that matter most, I reckon.
Interviewer: Your play Kindertransport is a set text in schools.
Do you think students can enjoy it just from reading it, or do they need to see a performance?
Diane: I have talked to many students and visited many schools
who study Kindertransport and the thing I find I do when I go in that often teachers aren’t doing
– if it’s in an English literature context, this is, ’cause it’s also studied in a drama context,
where of course their approach to it is to perform it.
So, there’s loads of students who study Kindertransport to actually mount a production of it,
or to mount a, you know, a series of performances of extracts.
So, in a sense, that feels to me to be the most rewarding way to study the play.
It isn’t – Kindertransport isn’t really, in itself, if you like, a work of literature.
So, you only touch the tip of the iceberg, just reading it, and I guess that’s true of Shakespeare,
you know, in answer to the earlier questions.
You’re not getting everything out of the play, which is maybe what Helen Mirren means.
Interviewer: Diane Samuels, thank you very much, it’s been a pleasure.